Mary Chrystie Papers, 1833-1841: Finding Aid
Cotsen Children's Library
- Correspondence, 1833-1841; 1830s-1840s; 15.0 folders (Box 1)
  - Letters to Mary Few, circa 1832-1833; 2.0 items
    - To Mary Few, circa 1832-1833; 1.0 pages 17.2 x 19.6 cm Includes pencil sketch. One sheet of ruled paper. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      No date (but stated in Frances' hand that Mary (her daughter) was "7 or 8 years of age" when she wrote the letter, hence 1832-1833?). A short note in which Mary mentions her brother's garden preparations and tells her aunt Mary that she is sending along two baskets, instructing her to "choose which you like best & give the other to Aunt Tildy". On verso is a pencil sketch of a farm yard scene and a poem (copied from an unknown source) entitled "The Shepard's Home".
  - Letters to Matilda Few, 1832 December; 1.0 item
    Mary Chrystie's letter to her Aunt Matilda "Tildy" Few, December 1832. The letter covers these topics of interest: Mary's dog Frisk, a local dog who sits in the church pew on Sundays, a hymn, and a pencil sketch of a tree.
    - Letter to Matilda Few, 1832 December; 2.0 pages 19.4 x 32.1 cm Pencil sketch on verso. One sheet. (Box 1, Folder 7)
      December 1832 (dated from a pencil written statement by Frances Chrystie, Mary's mother, on verso of letter), Fishkill Landing. Mary tells her "dear aunt Tildy" about her dog Frisk, his other canine friends, and another local dog that goes to church every Sunday and "sets up in the pew behind us and behaves like a gentleman". She asks Matilda to send down her lap dog and her cat. Since Mary is writing on a Sunday, she decides to transcribe a hymn, "Worth of the Bible". Mary mentions that she has "a very great secret which will surprise you very much", but she does not reveal it. Includes a pencil sketch of a tree on the verso.
  - Letters to Eliza Durham, Undated; 2.0 items
    Mary Chrystie's letters to her aunt Eliza Durham, no dates provided. Includes 2 letters from Mary mother, Frances, and 1 letter from Mary's brother, William. The letters cover these topics of interest: Mary's Christmas gifts, Frances's unhappiness caused by the death fo her grandmother, Mary's ailments, and the sickness of her friend Mrs. Schink, Mary's moral improvement, and a scarlet fever outbreak in Eliza Durham's area around Newburgh.
    - To Eliza Durham, December 19, no year; 4.0 pages 32.1 x 39.6 cm Large chunk of paper (approx. 6 x 16.3 cm) missing (does not affect text). One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 8)
      December 19 (no year), Fishkill Landing. 2 letters (1 from Mary and one from Mary's mother Frances). Although the letter is dated December 19, Mary states that it is Christmas Day. She goes on to enumerate the presents that she has recieved: "battledoor & shuttlecock - a sugar dog - a cornucopia full of sugar plums - a beautiful book full of pictures - and wooden cart made by her brother Willie". Frances expresses a great deal of unhappiness and weariness due largely, it seems, to the death of her grandmother: "dear Grandmama - everyday I feel her loss - I cannot express to you how interesting and how dear to me she was. Oh shall we ever meet & know & love again?". Adding to her melancholy feelings are the sickness of a good friend, Mrs. Schink, and Mary's continuing respiratory ailments. Frances closes by warning Eliza to regulate her affections for her pet (child?), Robert.
    - To Eliza Durham, undated; 2.0 pages 20.1 x 24.5 cm Letter is incomplete. One sheet. (Box 1, Folder 8)
      No date. 3 letters (1 from Mary, apparently at a very young age, 1 from Mary's brother William, and 1 from Mary's mother Frances). A short note from Mary and a short note from William. Frances describes Mary's moral improvement during the course of her winter studies with her mother and father: "[Mary] has certainly in the last year overcome many of her evil propensities & I think I can now pronounce her a child of truth". Frances also expresses her regrets that Eliza has been surrounded by the sickness and death brought about by an outbreak of scarlet fever (in Newburgh?). Frances's letter is incomplete, there appears to be a leaf missing.
  - Letters to Rhoda Bolton, 1840s; 4.0 items
    Chronological order, with undated item at end.
    Mary Chrystie's letters to her friend Rhoda Bolton. Spanning 1840-1841. The letters cover these topics of interest: salutations, a request for a visit form Rhoda, Mary is disappointed by postponed trips and a bout with the measles, includes a card.
    - To Rhoda Bolton, 1840 October 19; 4.0 pages 24.4 x 38.6 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 9)
      October 19, 1840, New York; postmarked October 21 at New York. Begins with salution "Dear Rosa" (a pet name, perhaps). At the time of this writing, Mary was studying in New York with a Miss Campbell. In this letter Mary writes to her Rhoda, a school friend from her time spent at Pelham Priory, instructing Rhoda to say hello to all of her other friends at Pelham Priory.
    - To Rhoda Bolton, 1841 March 26; 4.0 pages 25.7 x 30.7 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 9)
      March 26, 1841, New York; no postmark, but with a note on verso saying "Favoured by Mr. Jay Bolton". Mary requests that her friend Rhoda come visit her, if for no other reason than that she will then be familiar with Mary's surroundings and local friends; this, then, will allow Mary to write letters that will be both longer and of more interest to Rhoda.
    - To Rhoda Bolton, 1841 April 9; 4.0 pages 25.7 x 30.8 cm Dark green wax seal of the Eye of Providence, indecipherable text. One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 9)
      April 9, 1841, New York; postmarked May 1 at New York. Again beginning with a salutation to "dearest Rosa", Mary goes on to describe a series of disappointments to her friend including a number of postponed trips and a bout with measles; the letter begins: "I never met with more disappointments in my life I believe than I have within the last few weeks, I shall renumerate them to you, feeling sure you will sympathize with me".
    - To Rhoda Bolton, circa 1840-1841; 4.0 pages 11.2 x 17.5 cm 4 page card, with die-cut border (similar to lace) on the first leaf, folded into the shape of a triangle. (Box 1, Folder 9)
      No date, no place. A card to accompany a gift of "silk... meant for an apron" that Mary intends for her friend Rhoda to make.
  - Letters to Anne Chambreleng, 1835-1836; 2.0 items
    Mary Chrystie's letters to her friend Anne Cambreleng. Spanning: December 22, 1835 - January 18, 1836. The letters cover these topics of interest: a riddle, Mary's feelings about arriving at Princeton, and the Great Fire of 1835 (New York City).
    - To Anne Chambreleng, 1836 January 18; 4.0 pages 24.4 x 38.6 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 10)
      January 18, 1836, Princeton; Postmarked January 18 at Princeton. Mary Chrystie writes a newsy letter to her friend Anne Chambreleng in New York City. The letter includes a riddle (the same riddle Mary wrote for her mother Frances Chrystie in item 16 of the series "Letters to Frances Chrystie").
    - To Anne Chambreleng, 1835 December 22; 4.0 pages 24.4 x 39.2 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 10)
      December 22, 1835, Princeton (dated at the bottom of the page). Mary Chrystie sends her greetings to her friend Anne Chambreleng, saying that she has "been very well ever since [she] came [to Princeton]". Mary also mentions a large fire that has recenctly occured in New York City (later known as "The Great Fire of 1835").
  - Separately Collected Miscellaneous Letters, 1830s-1840s; 15.0 items
    Various letters, mostly by Mary Chrystie, written to members of Mary's family and her friends. Spanning: February 7, 1836 - July 10 1841. This group of letters was previously tied together by a piece of white ribbon still included in the series (probably collected by Mary Chrystie's mother Frances Chrystie after Mary's death). The letters cover these topics of interest: Mary's fleas, sicknesses, and posion ivy at Pelham Priory, Mary's fear of her music teacher, Mary's defence of Oliver Cromwell during a discussion about Cromwell and Charles I, Mary's own lesson plans for the coming winter at home including: French, writing, "sums", history, and astronomy, Mary's mother Frances Chrystie's anxieties over her daughter's health, Mary's time in the country, Mary's involvement in the courtship of her friend Louisa by a Mr. Beals, evidence of Frances Chrystie's collecting Mary's letters post mortem, Mary's new dog, a riddle, Mary's work for the poor, Revolutionary War sites near Pelham Priory, a letter writing game with friends at Pelham Priory, Mary's homesickness, a memorable trip to an island with a blind horse swimming, Mary's weight, and a prayer written by Mary.
    - To Frances Chrystie, circa 1840 August 27; 4.0 pages 25.3 x 39.8 cm One sheet folded in half (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Wednesday, August (circa 1840), Pelham Priory; postmarked August 27 at New Rochelle, New York. This letter appears to have been written after Mary wrote her August 17 letter to her great aunt Maria Montgomery (see series: Letters to Maria Montgomery, item 4). Mary Chrystie writes to her mother Frances Chrystie that she has been afflicted with flea bites (125 separate bites, by her own count), but that she is "growing used to them". She mentions that the "poison" she had referred to in her letter to Maria Montgomery, "is going away". She decribes her regimen of bathing in salt water and her decision to no longer use flaxseed to treat her ailments. She also mentions (as she had to Maria Montgomery) the loss of the brooch her brother gave her.
    - To Frances Chrystie, circa 1840 September 1; 4.0 pages 25.5 x 39.6 cm One sheet folded in half. Large chunk missing (approx. 5.5 x 19.3 cm) at bottom (does not affect text). (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Monday (no date), Pelham Priory; postmarked September 1 at New Rochelle, New York. Mary Chrystie again writes to her mother Frances Chrystie about her flea problem and notes that her "poison" is almost gone and "does not trouble me at all now, and only looks very ugly". Mary complains that her music teacher "is so hatefully cross that I tremble when she calls me to take my lesson" and mentions that her throat is "pretty well" but that she "wheeze[s] when the weather is at all damp".
    - To Frances Chrystie, circa 1840 September 14; 4.0 pages 25 x 40.4 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      September 14 (no year), Pelham Priory; postmarked September 19 at New Rochelle, New York; written at the top of the first page, underlined, and emphasized further by three exclamation marks is: "Only one month and two days!!!" - this is reemphasized in a postscript; Mary begins by telling her mother of her recent ill health (headaches, stomach pains, and fever), and closes after two pages; she reopens the letter and writes more later that evening, however, to tell her mother that she feels much improved, and that, in a dispute between the young ladies as to the relative merit of Oliver Cromwell and Charles I, she is the only one who has taken Cromwell's side; she closes the letter with a compliment she received from her teacher: "[Miss Bolton] says that she never knew any young person write with so much ease that my compositions are so natural not as if it was an effort to write."
    - To Frances Chrystie, 1840 September 28; 4.0 pages 25 x 40.3 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      September 28, 1840, Pelham Priory; labeled "(No 4)" in an unknown hand at top of first page; with her time at Pelham Priory coming to an end, Mary writes her mother to tell her that she still suffers from a cough, headaches, and a sore throat and asks if she can come home as soon as possible; most interesting are Mary's own lesson plans for her winter at home: she has 2 hours set aside with her father (bookeeping, sums, writing, spelling, and French), time spent studying history, notably "Ramsay's United States" (David Ramsay's History of the United States, unfinished at his death in 1815, but completed by his brother-in-law, S. Stanhope Smith; Ramsay was a graduate of Princeton in 1765) with her mother, and supplemental learning with a number of composition books, reading a dictionary, and memorizing French phrases and verbs, with, perhaps, some readings from "Banicastle's astronomy" (John Bonnycastle's Introduction to Astronomy, London, 1796), with music and painting filling in the rest of her time.
    - To Catherine Few, Undated; 4.0 pages 24.5 x 40 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Monday (no date), postmarked January (?) 16 at Fishkill Landing; from Mary Chrystie's mother, Frances Chrystie. A rather melancholy letter full of thoughts of loss and death as Mrs. Chrystie describes Mary's continuing ill-health (from a present case of "whooping cough," Mrs. Chrystie says); her anxiety for Mary and the severity of Mary's illness are testified by the following lines: "Sometimes I have a glimpse of things as they are in this world and then I can undeservedly give her up to God and say Thy will be done--but too often I cannot even bear to think of parting with her--she is a dear little creature and tho' full of faults I am sure if she is spared she will be a good woman..."; Mrs. Chrystie then goes on to describe the failing health of a number of other women in the neighborhood.
    - To Mary Few, 1841 July 10; 4.0 pages 25.2 x 39.8 cm One sheet folded in half, with substantial remains of dark green wax seal (with "Mary" still legible). (Box 1, Folder 11)
      July 10, 1841, Lebanon; 2 letters (1 from Mary Chrystie and 1 from her mother, Frances Chrystie); with substantial remains of a dark green wax seal (with "Mary" still legible). Mary describes her time in the country, with particular attention paid to the dogs, kittens, and birds around the farm at which she is staying; Mary also excitedly relates that she has "been made the confidant in love affairs, an office which I like very much, as I have love letters read to me" (the love letters are from a Mr. Beals and are directed to Mary's friend(?) Louisa). Frances Chrystie, Mary Chrystie's mother, complains that she has not had a letter in some time, and mentions that Mary is gaining strength and that Albert Chrystie, Frances' husband, is suffering from some sort of "dispeptic feeling which occasions an irregularity of his pulse."
    - To Matilda Few, Undated; 4.0 pages 24.6 x 40.3 cm One sheet folded in half. Fragile. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      No date; postmarked February 4 at Fishkill Landing; from Frances Chrystie, Mary Chrystie's mother. A newsy letter in which Frances Chrystie professes that she is quite comfortable and content with her increasingly grey hair and expresses her uneasiness over Mary's poor health; winter at Fishkill Landing is very pleasant, and she spends the rest of the letter describing the health and affairs of people from the neighborhood.
    - To Eliza Durham, Undated; 4.0 pages 25.5 x 40.6 cm One sheet folded in half. Large chunk (approx. 6.9 x 20.3 cm) cut and missing (does not affect text). Very fragile condition, with paper beginning to separate along some of the folds. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      No date; postmarked February 17 from New York; from Frances Chrystie, Mary Chrystie's mother. Written to the side of the address block is a note in a different ink: "Letters in which my child is mentioned"--evidence of Frances Chrystie's attempt to gather materials by and concerning Mary after her death; Frances Chrystie writes about her great pleasure at wintering in the city and states that she is so content that "no change for me can be for the better"; Willie (William, Mary Chrystie's brother) and Mary are now studying under a new teacher who is much loved and respected by his pupils; Mary wheezes on occasion, but her health has largely been sound.
    - To Rhonda Bolton, 1841 January 5; 4.0 pages 25.8 x 30.8 cm One sheet folded in half. A hole in the second leaf (presumably made when the wax seal was removed) affects the text. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      January 5, 1841, New York; postmarked January 8 at New York; from Mary Chrystie. Mary apologizes for not having written sooner, but she has a good excuse: "I have been obliged to keep my room (and part of the time my bed) for nearly three weeks with an inflammation of my lungs"; she describes in detail her new dog--which she has named Rhoda in honor of her friend ("I hope you are able to appreciate the honour conferred on you..."); she explains that due to her illness she will not attend school "for some time"; Mary copies a long riddle for Rhoda to solve. A hole in the second leaf (presumably made when the wax seal was removed) affects the text.
    - To Anna Cambreling (sic), circa 1840 August 19; 4.0 pages 25.3 x 39.8 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Dated August 19 (no year, but circa 1840), Pelham Priory; Postmarked August 22 at New Rochelle, New York; from Mary Chrystie. Labeled "(No 2)" in an unknown hand on top of first page. A very newsy and interesting letter in which Mary describes her life and surroundings at Pelham Priory; she is involved in "a little scoiety...to work for the poor in the neighborhood" (sewing for poor families) and it is while delivering some of the clothes they have prepared that Mary, in an attempt to skirt around a swampy area, falls off a fence into some bushes and brambles concealing "poison vines"--the cause of Mary's "poisoning" mentioned in a letter to her great aunt and to her mother (see Letters to Maria Montgomery 4 and Miscellaneous Letters 1 and 2). Mary describes numerous Revolutionary War sites in the area, including an immense rock in the forest used by Americans to grind corn, the "haunted oak" where "several men were hung...during the war," and small spring where two Americans were shot by the British while having a drink; she also describes an interesting Irishman ("quite an original character"), a workman at the Priory; and she describes a "post office" that she and her friends have established at which they deposit letters they write to each other under fictitious names (Mary is Lady Albertine Collona of Geneva, Switzerland, but she is considering changing her name to Biddy O'Brian of Cork, Ireland); Mary also transcribes a letter she has received from the "Duke of Wellington," written by Ada Bolton.
    - To Anne Cambreleng, 1841 July 6; 4.0 pages 25.7 x 40.9 cm One sheet folded in half. With substantial remains of dark green wax seal (with "Mary" still legible). Very fragile condition; paper beginning to separate along some of the folds. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Dated July 6, 1841, Lebanonville; from Mary Chrystie; with substantial remains of dark green wax seal (with "Mary" still legible). Mary writes from her uncle's (Albert Chrystie's brother's) house in the country; she spends much of her time with her friend Louisa, but their "amusements together have lately been very much interrupted by [Louisa's] lover's (a Mr. Beals)" visits; Louisa's engagement to Mr. Beals is back on after her sister, who, Mary says, did not approve of the match, persuaded Louisa that she did not love him enough; Mary describes other activities, such as driving with her father, and expresses concern for her dog, who has been left at home with the servants.
    - To Anna (sic) Cambreleng, circa 1837-1840 September 1; 4.0 pages 25.3 x 39.8 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Circa 1837-1840; postmarked September 1 at New Rochelle, New York; from Mary Chrystie. A long letter written with crossed, overlapping text throughout in which Mary describes her homesickness and a very memorable picnic trip with all the other students at Pelham Priory (Mary also includes a complete list of names of the people who went on the picnic--31 people in all) to a nearby island; while sailing to the island Mary's boat discovers a blind horse swimming away from land and rescues it; a rush to be seated on an old, rotting bench results of many of her classmates being deposited on the ground "in a number of very interesting positions"; Mary also describes a singing game played between the two boat-loads of students, and transcribes the text of a sung prayer used that day at lunch. Dates supplied are the probable years which Mary spent at Pelham Priory.
    - To Anne Cambreleng, circa 1837-1840; 4.0 pages 25 x 30.5 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Pelham Priory, circa 1837-1840; postmarked September 17 at new Rochelle, New York; Labeled "(No 3)" in an unknown hand at top of first page; from Mary Chrystie. Mary, addressing Anne as "Nancy," describes another picnic, including a tree where a young man named Underhill "hung himself in a fit of melancholy"; Mary steps onto a scale in a mill and is surprised to discover that she weighs only 85 pounds; she mentions that she has been "quite sick" but is now well; and she scolds Anne for not writing more often: "I have had twenty two letters since I have been here, and only three from you." Dates supplied are the probable years which Mary spent at Pelham Priory.
    - A Prayer Written by Mary, 1836 February 7; 1.0 pages 12.9 x 20.5 cm One ruled sheet. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Dated on the verso in Frances Chrystie's, her mother's hand(?): "Written.Feb.7.1836." Entitled "Prayer to God"; Mary prays for an "aimiable and benevolent" temper and for God to "soften our hard and stony hearts so that we may be brought to love thee and serve thee as we ought"; she also prays for the missionary cause and for the protection of those who leave home and have "gone to foreign lands and have taught the poor heathen natives the truth of the holy Bible."
    - Ribbon used to tie together letters, undated; 1.0 item Approximately 50 cm in length. White ribbon used to tie together items in series ("Miscellaneous Letters"). Tied in a loop. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      White ribbon used to tie together items in series ("Miscellaneous Letters"). Tied in a loop.
  - Prayers, Poems, and Miscellaneous Notes Written by Mary Chrystie, 1833-1872; 11.0 items
    Prayers, poems, fiction, and journal entries by Mary Chrystie, some original, some copied from periodicals and other publications. Most are undated, but span the period January 21 1833 - May 23 1872; some are materials related to Mary collected by relatives and friends after her death. Topics of interest include: Mary's religious disposition at a young age, her relationship with God, her rasising of horses, her feelings toward her mother, and her stories about children.
    - Prayer: "Oh! my most gracious Redeemer...", 1836 December; 4.0 pages 14.7 x 9.8 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      A touching and selfless prayer of dedication: "Oh! my most gracious Redeemer I now give myself to thee in my presence. I will solemnly give my word that I will henceforth deem thy word as sacred and thous as without blemish. I pray thee Oh! Lord to help me fulfil (sic) my resolutions to become thy servent (sic) forever and I shall not leave out my dear brother and parents and all my friends and particularly my dear cousin Mag and forgive them all their sins and give me my dear mother's head-ache and take it from her. Your sinful servent (sic) Mary Chrystie."; on verso is a note written in her mother's hand: "princeton Dec 1836 Found by her Mother," and another note written by Mary: "Hoped to be opened next time with joy"; This item was enclosed in a folded paper with writing by her mother (see next item).
    - Note by Frances Chrystie on a prayer by Mary Chrystie, Undated; 4.0 pages 18.5 x 22.6 cm One sheet folded in half. (Box 1, Folder 12)